in 1978 satellites began continuously
observing the polar regions and the
dynamic beauty of the Arctic sea ice was
revealed what we expect to be a solid
mass of ice is actually in constant
motion as researchers continue to seek a
deeper understanding of this region new
information about how sea ice changes is
coming to light in this animation we're
taking Arctic sea ice into the third
dimension here
we're looking at the ice age which is an
indicator of thickness generally older
ice is thicker ice that's the voice of
dr. waltemeyer senior research scientist
at the National snow and ice data center
what you see in this animation is free
ice pulsing out and in with the seasons
in winter the ice grows out and expands
outward and summer it contracts inward
as it melts you see the whiter ice which
is the older ice moving around the
Arctic being pushed around by winds and
currents that move the ice
[Music]
over the years the ice pulses around and
moves around towards the top along the
coast of Greenland the older ice
eventually moves out of the Arctic and
into the North Atlantic where it melts
the ice gets replenished within the
Arctic because some of the ice survives
each summer and grows older and
particularly in the region north of
Alaska called the Beaufort Sea where the
ice spins around in a clockwise
direction called the Beaufort gyre and
that ice can keep spinning around
oftentimes for several years and
gradually getting older and thus getting
thicker eventually the ice will spin out
of that dryer and go out through Fram
Strait in the past we've always had
enough ice growth and ice aging enough
ice surviving the summers to replenish
the older ice that's lost but in recent
years we've seen less replenishment
there's been more melt during the summer
so the ice that goes out through Fram
Strait has not been compensated by the
ice growth in addition especially in
recent years we've seen some pretty
remarkable things in the Beaufort Sea
where that area that used to be a
nursery for the development of the older
ice allow the young ice to age and
mature what we've seen instead is the
ice is now more broken up more scattered
and that's allowing the older ice to
melt within the Beaufort Sea so we're
seeing the Beaufort Sea go from a
nursery to a graveyard for older ice as
we get towards the more recent years
much of that oldest ice the ice that's
older than five years old in the bright
white is almost virtually disappeared
from the Arctic Ocean and the Arctic is
now dominated by younger and thinner ice
you